<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A confession and profession of faith in God: by his people who are inscorn [sic] called Quakers. Also shewing that the people of God are no vagabonds, nor idle, dissolute persons, nor Jesuites, though they wander up and down, and pass from one country to another, and from one nation to another, as they are moved of the Lord in his service. And this is to clear the truth from all false aspersions. By R. Farnsvvorth.</title>
            <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85134</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F478</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E935_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202127</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862529</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862529</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114692</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85134)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114692)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 140:E935[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A confession and profession of faith in God: by his people who are inscorn [sic] called Quakers. Also shewing that the people of God are no vagabonds, nor idle, dissolute persons, nor Jesuites, though they wander up and down, and pass from one country to another, and from one nation to another, as they are moved of the Lord in his service. And this is to clear the truth from all false aspersions. By R. Farnsvvorth.</title>
                  <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 [i.e. 16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Giles Calvert at the Black-spread-Eagle near the vvest-end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1958 [i.e. 1598]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Actual publication date from Wing.</note>
                  <note>P. 16 misnumbered 14.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114692:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114692:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CONFESSION AND Profeſsion of Faith IN GOD: <hi>By his People who are in ſcorn called</hi> QVAKERS.</p>
            <p>ALSO SHEWING That the People of God are no <hi>Vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonds,</hi> nor <hi>Idle, Diſſolute Perſons,</hi> nor <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites,</hi> though they wander up and down, and paſs from one Country to another, and from one Nation to another, as they are moved of the Lord in his ſervice.</p>
            <p>And this is to clear the Truth from all falſe <hi>Aſperſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>R. FARNSVVORTH.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the Black-ſpread-Eagle near the VVeſt-end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1958.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="profession_of_faith">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:114692:2"/>
            <head>A CONFESSION AND PROFESSION OF Faith in God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>TO all true<note n="(a)" place="margin">Act. 11.26.</note> Chriſtians Gods<note n="(b)" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</note> Elect, and<note n="(c)" place="margin">Phil. 1.1, 2.</note> Saint; of the moſt High God, who are begotten by the<note n="(d)" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.22, 23. Joh. 3.5, 6</note> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Word, and born again of Water and the Spirit; The Church<note n="(e)" place="margin">Col. 1.18. Eph. 1.22, 23. Eph: 5.26, 27.</note> of which Chriſt Jeſus is (in the Holy Scriptures) declared to be the Head: And to all faithful moderate People whomſoever, whereſoever, and by what Names and Title: ſoever known by, or diſtinguiſhed to (or amongſt) the ſons of men; know ye hereby aſſuredly, That we who of the world are ſlanderouſly reported (as the people of God were in former ages, <hi>Rom. 3.8.</hi>) and who are reproachfully called Quakers, do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, and confeſs, teſtifie, own, believe, and declare as followeth:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THat we Profeſs and Confeſs Faith in God the Father, and in Jeſus Chriſt his eternal Son, the true God; and in the Holy Spirit: And we do acknowledge the Holy Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament to be the Words of God: This we teſtifie; and we are not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114692:2"/>
aſhamed to Confeſs and Profeſs Faith in God the Father, and in Chriſt Jeſus his eternal Son, and in the Holy Spirit, as the Scriptures ſaith; but we do believe in them, and acknowledge ſubjection and dutiful obedience unto them,</hi> viz. <hi>The Father, Son, and Holy Spirit: And moreover we do hereby declare and teſtifie to all true Chriſtians Gods Elect, what God we do own, and profeſs Faith in even in that God that appeared unto</hi> Abraham, (<hi>the Father of the Faithful, when</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham <hi>was ninty nine years old) and ſaid unto him,</hi> I am the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God walk before me, and be thou perfect, <hi>Gen. 17.1.</hi> The everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting God, <hi>Gen. 21.33.</hi> The God of Heaven and Earth, <hi>Gen. 24.3.</hi> The God of Truth, who is juſt and right, and without iniquity, <hi>Deut. 32.3, 4.</hi> The faithful God, that keepeth Covenant and Mercy with them that love him, and keepeth his Commandments, to a thouſand Generations, <hi>Deut. 7.9.</hi> The faithful and merciful God, who will not ſuffer his to be tempted above that which they are able, but will with the temptation alſo make a way to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape, that they may be able to bear it, <hi>1 Cor 10.13.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.3. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.2.</note> He is a God of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and by him actions are weighed, <hi>1 Sam. 2.3.</hi> Neither is there any Rock like our God, <hi>1 Sam. 2.2.</hi> As for God his way is perfect, the Word of the Lord is tryed, he is a buckler to all them that put their truſt in him, <hi>2 Sam. 22.31.</hi> and therefore he is worthy to be believed, and have Faith in him pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, for who is God ſave the Lord, and who is a rock ſave our God, <hi>2 Sam. 22.32, 33.</hi> He is the great, the mighty, and the terrible God, <hi>Neh. 9.32.</hi> That God who is the King of all the earth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.21, 22. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.5.</note> who reigneth over the Heathen, and ſitteth upon the throne of his Holineſs, <hi>Pſal. 47.7, 8.</hi> A juſt God and a Saviour, <hi>Iſa. 45.21, 22.</hi> Thus ſaith the Lord, the King of Iſrael, and his Redeemer, The Lord of Hoſts, I am the firſt, and I am the laſt, and beſides me there is no God, as you may read, <hi>Iſa. 44.6. Iſa. 43.11, 12.</hi> Who is a God near at hand, as well as a far off, <hi>Jer. 23.23.</hi> That God who dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in the high and holy place, with him alſo that is of a contrite and humble ſpirit, <hi>Iſa. 57.15.</hi> Yea, the God of patience and conſolation, <hi>Rom. 15.5.</hi> the God of hope, <hi>Rom. 15.13.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iude</hi> 25.</note> and that God who is the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Father of all Mercies, and the God of all Comfort, <hi>2 Cor. 1.3.</hi> The God of Love and Peace, <hi>2 Cor. 13.11.</hi> The King eternal, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, inviſible, the only wiſe God, <hi>1 Tim. 1.17.</hi> God who is Light, and in him is no darkneſs at all, <hi>1 Joh. 1.5.</hi> The only true God, <hi>Joh. 17.3.</hi> and the Lord our God is one Lord, <hi>Mark 12.29.</hi> For there is one God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 12.29, 30, 31, 32, 33, 34. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5, 6.</note> and there is none other but he, <hi>Mark 12.32.34.</hi> And there is none other God but one, <hi>1 Cor. 8.4. Iſa. 44.8.</hi> And this is God the Father which we own, and profeſs Faith in, and in Chriſt Jeſus his eternal Son, who ſaid, I and my Father are one, <hi>Joh. 10.30.</hi> (upon which ſaying, the <hi>Jews</hi> took up ſtones to ſtone him, <hi>Joh. 10.30, 31.</hi>) yet notwithſtanding the ſame Chriſt that the <hi>Jews</hi> hated, we love, believe in, and own, who was delivered up to be cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for our offences; and was raiſed again for our juſtification, <hi>Rom. 4.25.</hi> Who is the true God, and him we own, and profeſs Faith in, and in the Holy
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114692:3"/>
Spirit, God; together equal with the Father, and the Son, one God over all, God bleſſed for ever, <hi>Iſa. 45.6. Joh. 10.30. Rom. 8, 9, 10, 11. Eph. 4.4, 5. Eph. 4.30.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 9.5.</note> 
               <hi>1 Cor. 2.10, 12. Joh. 4.24. Rom. 9.5.</hi> And unto (us and al true Chriſtians) the Saints in Chriſt Jeſus; <hi>Phil. 1.1.</hi> It is given in the behalf of Chriſt, not onely to beleeve on him, but alſo to ſuffer for his names ſake; <hi>As you may read Phil. 1.29.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>As concerning the Scriptures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>That which in the holy Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament is declared and teſtifyed of to be the Word of God, that we beleeve in, own, and confeſs to be the word of God, according to the Scriptures; And that the holy Scriptures of the old and new Teſtament, as they are the Words of God, ſo to be we own, Knowing this firſt, <hi>that no prophecie of the Scripture came in old time by the will of man, but holy men of God ſpoke as they were moved by the holy Ghoſt,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.21. <hi>Who propheſied of the grace that should come unto the Saints</hi> [and us] <hi>in after a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, ſearching what or what manner of time, the Spirit of Chriſt which was in them did ſignifie, when it teſtified before-hand the Sufferings of Chriſt, and the glory that should follow, unto whom it was revealed, that not unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves but unto us they did Miniſter the things which are now declared unto you, by them that have preached the Goſpel unto you, with the holy Ghoſt ſent down from heaven;</hi> 1 Pet. 1.10, 11, 12. <hi>And God ſpake all theſe words ſaying, I am the Lord thy God, &amp;c.</hi> Exod. 20. ch. So the words and ſayings of God we do not deny, but own them ſo to be, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Scriptures of the old and new Teſtament as aforeſaid: But unto the Wicked God ſaith, <hi>What haſt thou to do to declare my ſtatutes? or that thou shouldſt take my covenant into thy mouth? ſeeing thou hateſt inſtruction, and caſteſt my words behind thee,</hi> as you may read <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.16, 17. As the holy Scriptures are the words of God, ſo the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed are not allowed nor appointed by the Lord to preach or declare them, as the ſtatutes of God, nor take his covenant into their mouth, as God hath ſaid: And the reaſon is, becauſe they hate inſtructions and caſt his words behind them: But ſuch as are inſtructed and taught of the Lord,<note place="margin">Iſa. 48.16, 17, &amp;c. 1 Pet. 4.10, 11.</note> who love his Inſtruction, and hear his word, they may preach and declare his ſtatutes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as they are thereunto directed and led by the holy ſpirit of the Lord; for <hi>the words of the Lord are pure words, as ſilver tryed in a furnace of earth, ſeven times purified;</hi> as the Scriptures teſtifieth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12.6. <hi>Have not I written unto thee excellent things in counſell and knowledge? that I might make thee know the certainty of the words of truth, that thou mighteſt anſwer the words of Truth to them that ſend unto thee.</hi> Prov. 22.20, 21.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the preparation of the heart in man (that</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 50.4, 5 Lu. 12.12.</note> 
                  <hi>is taught of God) and the anſwer of the tongue is from the Lord;</hi> Prov. 16.1. And ſaith
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114692:3"/>
the Lord, <hi>Ye shall lay up theſe my words in your heart, and in your ſoul,</hi> as you may read, <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.18. And again ſaith the Lord, <hi>obſerve and hear all theſe words which I command thee, that it may go well with thee,</hi> and as you may read, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.28. <hi>But</hi> [ſaith the Lord] <hi>if they had ſtood in my counſel, and had cauſed my people to hear my words, then they should have turned them from their evil ways, and from the evil of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> as you may read, <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.21. And ſaith the Prophet <hi>Ieremiah, Mine heart within me is broken, becauſe of the Prophets; All my bones shake, I am like a drunken man, and like a man whom wine hath overcome, becauſe of the Lord, and becauſe of the words of his holineſs,</hi> as you may read <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.9. But if that true prophet of the Lord had been here now, and his bones had ſhaked, would he not have been mocked, and reproachfully called <hi>A Quaker</hi> or <hi>Shaker,</hi> &amp;c. and might he not have been excommunicated, or caſt out from amongſt men, as <hi>A Quaker,</hi> without any juſt cauſe, and all ſuch alſo as trembled at the word of the Lord, as many now adaies are; and for being faithful to the Lord, and owning his power, and the words of his holineſs, as the true Prophet did; But the Prophet <hi>Ezra</hi> ſaith as followeth, <hi>Then were aſſembled unto me every one that trembled at the words of the God of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael;</hi> as you may read, <hi>Ez.</hi> 9.4. And ſaith the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel, The word of the Lord came unto me, ſaying, Son of man, Eat thy bread with quaking, and drink thy water with trembling, &amp;c.</hi> Eze. 12.17, 18 There was the word of the Lord that came to him, and here are the words and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings that proceeded from the word; But if any eat their bread with Quakeing, and drink their Water with trembling now, according to the ſayings of God declared from the word of the Lord, will they not be mocked and called <hi>Quakers</hi> in much ſcorn? And muſt they not for owning the power of God, and his works, be caſt out from the ſocieties of great profeſſing men: Would not ſuch have caſt out the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> and ſuch as theſe Scriptures makes mention of, if they had been here in theſe times, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 12.17, 18. <hi>Dan.</hi> 10.7, 8, 9, 10, 11. <hi>Iob</hi> 21.5, 6. <hi>Iob</hi> 37.1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.8. <hi>Pſal</hi> 55.2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.120. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.2, 5. <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.9. <hi>Ier.</hi> 30.5.6, 7. <hi>Acts</hi> 7.32. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.21.</p>
               <p>And ſaith the Lord unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> who trembled at the word of the Lord, and did fear<note n="†" place="margin">Act. 7.31, 32. Heb. 12.21.</note> and quake, <hi>I will raiſe them up a Prophet from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong their Brethren, like unto thee; and will put my words in his mouth and he shall ſpeak unto them all that I command him,</hi> Deut. 18.18, 19 And ſaith the Lord by the Prophet, <hi>I have put my words in thy mouth,</hi> Iſa. 51.16. <hi>As for me, this is my covenant with them ſaith the Lord, my ſpirit that is upon thee, &amp; my words which I have put in thy mouth, shall not depart out of thy mouth; nor out of the mouth of thy ſeed, nor out of the mouth of thy ſeeds ſeed, ſaith the Lord, from henceforth for ever;</hi> as you may read <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.21. <hi>Every word of God is pure, he is a shield to them
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114692:4"/>
them that put their truſt in him; Ad thou not unto his words, leſt he reprove, thee, and thou be found a Lyar,</hi> Prov. 30.5, 6. And ſaith Chriſt Jeſus, the eternal ſon of God,<note place="margin">Math. 7.24, 25, 26.27, 28, 29. Joh. 15.7. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.2 Jude 17.</note> and the true God, <hi>he that is of God heareth Gods words,</hi> John 8.47. <hi>And becauſe we are of God,</hi> 1 John 4.6. and hear his words, we are bound as a neceſſary duty to profeſs faith in him, and do confeſs it before men; And they that are aſhamed to do it, they may juſtly fear that Chriſt will be aſhamed of them: For ſaith Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, <hi>Whoſoever therefore shall be ashamed of me, and of my words in this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterous and ſinful generation; of him alſo shall the ſon of man be ashamed when he cometh in the glory of his Father, with the holy Angels:</hi> as you may read <hi>Mark</hi> 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.</p>
               <p>And that which in the holy Scriptures of the old and new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is declared by the holy Spirit, to be the eternal word of God; That we beleeve in, own, and confeſs to be the word of God, <hi>which liveth and abideth forever;</hi> as the Scriptures ſaith, and as you may read 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.22, 23. <hi>Through faith we underſtand, that the Worlds were framed by the word of God,</hi> as you may read <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.3. <hi>God who as ſundry times and in divers manners ſpoke in times paſt unto the Fathers by the Prophets, hath in theſe laſt dayes ſpoken unto us by his Son,</hi> whoſe name is called the word of God; <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.13. <hi>Whom he hath appointed Heir of all things, by whom alſo he made the worlds,</hi> as you may read, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.1, 2. <hi>And he upholdeth all things by the word of his power,</hi> ver. 3. <hi>In whom we have redemption through his bloud, even the forgiveneſs of ſins, who is the Image of the inviſible God, for by him were all things created that are in heaven, and that are in earth; and he is before all things, and by him all things conſist?</hi> as you may read <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.14, 15, 16, 17. <hi>For the word of God is quick and powerful,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 1.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</note> 
                  <hi>sharper then any two edged ſword, pierceing, even to the devideing aſunder of ſoul and ſpirit, and of the joints and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and is a diſcerner of the thoughts and intents of the heart; neither is there any creature that is not manifest in his ſight: but all things are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and opened unto the eyes of him, with whom we have to do: ſeeing then that we have a great high Priest, that is paſsed into the heavens, Ieſus the ſon of God: Let us hold faſt our profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 4.15, 16.</note> as the Scriptures ſaith, and as you may read, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12.13.14. <hi>Of his own will begat he us with the word of truth, that we should be a kinde of firſt fruits of his creatures,</hi> as you may read, <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Wherefore lay apart all filthineſs, and ſuperfluity of naughtineſs, and receive with meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the ingrafted word,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jam. 1.21.</note> 
                  <hi>which is able to ſave your ſouls:</hi> as you may read <hi>Iames</hi> 1.21. <hi>As ye have therefore received Chriſt Ieſus the Lord, ſo walk ye in him,</hi> Coloſ. 2.6, 7. <hi>The righteouſneſs of faith ſpeaketh on this wiſe, ſay not in thy heart, who shall aſcend into heaven, that is to bring Christ down from aboue, or who shall deſcend into the deep, that is to bring up Chriſt again from the dead: But what ſaith it? The word is nigh thee in thy mouth and in thy heart,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 30.11, 12, 13, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>that is the word of faith which we preach;</hi> as
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114692:4"/>
the Scripture teſtifieth, as you may read, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.6, 7, 8. <hi>For We preach not our ſelves but Chriſt Ieſus the Lord,</hi> as you may read, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5, 6, 7. <hi>Therefore they went every where preaching the word,</hi> Act. 8.6. <hi>Then Philip went down to Samaria, and preached Chriſt unto them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 8.5.</note> Act. 8.5. And as concerning the Goſpel of Chriſt, and the Declaration of the Goſpel, we are not aſhamed to confeſs; for <hi>the Goſpel it is the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God unto ſalvation, to every one that beleeveth, for therein is the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of God revealed from faith to faith, as it is written, the juſt shall live by his faith,</hi> and as you may read, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16, 17. And as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Declaration; <hi>Moreover Brethren, I declare unto you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.1, 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Lu: 1.1, 2.</note> 
                  <hi>the Goſpell which I preached unto you which alſo you have received, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ye stand, by which alſo ye are ſaved, unleſs ye have beleeved in vain, for I delivered unto you first of all that which I alſo received how that Chriſt dyed for our ſins, according to the Scriptures, and that he was buryed, and that he roſe again the third day, according to the ſcriptures, &amp;c.</hi> as you may read in the Declaration of the Goſpel, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>But the word of the Lord endureth for ever: And this is the word which by the Goſpel is preached unto you,</hi> Rom. 1.16, 17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1 Pet. 1.25. <hi>For this the mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and ſcoffers that were foretold of, and are come in theſe laſt dayes, who walk after their own luſts,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.3 <hi>they willingly are ignorant of; That by the word of God the heavens were of old, and the earth ſtanding out of the Water and in the Water,</hi> as the ſcripture ſaith, and as you may read, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.2, 3, 4, 5. <hi>Whereby the World that then was, being overflowed with Water perished:</hi> ver. 6. <hi>But the heavens and the earth which are now by the ſame word are kept in ſtore, reſerved unto fire againſt the day of judgement, and perdition of ungodly men:</hi> as you may read 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7. <hi>For by the word of the Lord were the heavens made,</hi> Pſal. 33.6. <hi>Therefore above all things take the shield of faith, wherewith ye shall be able to quench all the fiery darts of the Wicked; and take the helmet of ſalvation, and the ſword of the ſpirit, which is the Word of God:</hi> The<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 19.13, 15. Heb. 4.12. Eph. 6.17:</note> Word of God is the ſword of the ſpirit, and the ſword of the ſpirit is the word of God: <hi>Wherefore pray alwayes with all prayer and ſupplication in the ſpirit</hi> (for<note n="†" place="margin">Phil: 4:6. 1 Pe: 3.12. Rom 12.12 Joh: 4.23, 24. Phil: 3.3. Epheſ: 4.4, 5, 6, 7.</note> prayer is an ordinance of God) <hi>&amp; watch thereunto with al perſeverance and ſupplication for all ſaints,</hi> Eph. 10, 17, 18. <hi>Building up your ſelves (ye beloved) on your moſt holy faith praying in the holy Ghoſt;</hi> as you may read <hi>Jud.</hi> 20. <hi>Rom:</hi> 8.26, 27. 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 4.7.</p>
               <p>And as we profeſs faith in God the Father, and Chriſt Jeſus his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſon, &amp; in the holy ſpirit, as the ſcripture ſaith, &amp; own the word of God, &amp; prayer, &amp; the ordinances &amp; worſhip of God in ſpirit &amp; truth, acording to the ſcriptures; ſo likewiſe among the reſt, we own Miniſtry &amp; Magiſtracy to be ordinances of God, acording to the holy ſcriptures; For as it ſaith, <hi>there is one body &amp; one ſpirit, one Lord, one faith, one baptiſm, one God and Father;</hi> ſo likewiſe it is ſaid of Chriſt, <hi>that when he aſcended up on high, he gave gifts unto men; For he gave ſome Apoſtles, ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114692:5"/>
and ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome Paſtors and teachers. For this end that is to ſay, the perfecting of the Saints for the work of the Miniſtery, for the edifying of the body of Chriſt, til we all come in the unity of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God, unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulnes of Chriſt,</hi> as you may read, <hi>Ep</hi> 4.7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12 13. See 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 4.10, 11. Alſo ſee <hi>Rom:</hi> 12.6, 7, 8. <hi>And let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher power, for there it no power</hi> [which the ſoul is to be ſubject to] <hi>but of God, whoſoever therefore reſiſteth the power, reſiſteth the ordinance of God, and they that reſiſt the power and ordinance of God, shall receive to themſelves damnation</hi> Rom. 13.1, 2. <hi>For Rulers</hi> (that rule for God in his power and ordinance as aforeſaid, they) <hi>are not a terror to good works but to the evil.</hi> But if they rule not in the power of God, by which they are to diſcern and judge between good and evil: it will be otherwiſe yet, acting and ruleing in the power of God, they are for the encouragement and praiſe of them that do well, and ſo are to them the Miniſters of God for good: as you may read <hi>Rom:</hi> 13.3, 4.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Magiſtracy that rules for God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MOreover, how Magiſtrates that rules for God, according to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> holy ſcriptures of the old and new Teſtament are to be qualified, and by what power, and for whom they are to act; <hi>The ſpirit of the Lord ſpake by me, and the God of Iſrael ſaid, he that ruleth over men must be juſt, fearing God,</hi> as you may read, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.2, 3. <hi>Rulers</hi> [for God] <hi>muſt be juſt men, and fearing God,</hi> as God hath ſaid; <hi>and ſuch are as the light of the morning, when the ſun ariſeth without clouds,</hi> ver. 4. Therefore they that are ſo muſt needs be good examples, and not hate the light in others, nor them that walk in the pure Religion; ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of <hi>Jam:</hi> 1.27. <hi>Which is to viſit the Widdows and Fatherleſs in their diſtreſs, and to keep themſelves unſpotted of the World. When the righteous are in authority the</hi> [good] <hi>people rejoice; but when the wicked beareth rule the</hi> [good] <hi>people mourn:</hi> Prov: 29.2. <hi>For the righteous conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the cauſe of the poor, but the wicked regardeth not to know it,</hi> verſe 7. <hi>And if a Ruler hearken to lyes all his ſervants are wicked:</hi> as you may read <hi>Prov:</hi> 29.12. Therefore how juſt and upright ought Rulers to be, that they may not encourage the wicked, and cauſe them to rejoice in their wickedneſs, and cauſe the godly to mourn and be ſad: Judges &amp; officers which God comanded and ordained in the time of old, to be ſet up in all the gates throughout the Tribes. 1. They was to judge the people with juſt Judgement. 2. They were not to wreſt Judgement. 3. They was not to reſpect perſons. 4. They was not to take a gift, for the Lord ſaith, <hi>A gift doth blind the eyes of the wiſe:</hi> And 5. They was not to pervert the words of the righteous. But, 6. That which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114692:5"/>
was altogether juſt they was to follow as the Lord hath ſaid, and as you may read <hi>Deut.</hi> 16.18, 19, 20. And 7. When a controverſie did ariſe between man and man, ſo that it came before the Judges to be determined, the Judges was enjoined by the Law of God to make diligent Inquiſition, to the end that they might before judgement, find out the truth or falſhood of the Witneſſes: and if the judge by diligent enquiry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> found out the Witneſs to be a falſe Witneſs, and teſtifie a falſe thing againſt another: 8. Then he was to have paſſed the ſame judgement upon the falſe Witneſs, that he ſhould have done upon the other that he witneſſed againſt, if his teſtimony had been true; as you may read <hi>Deut.</hi> 19.15.16. to the end of the chapter. Judges are forbidden by the Lord, and by his Law to wreſt the Judgement of the poor in his cauſe, as aforeſaid. And 9. Judges and officers are required by the Law of God, to keep them far from a falſe matter. 10. &amp; the Lord doth forbid Judges, for ſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (by falſe judgement) the innocent and righteous; and again Judges are forbidden takeing a guift; as you may read, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.6.7, 8.11. Alſo the Lord ſaith, <hi>Thou shalt not raiſe a falſe report.</hi> 12. <hi>Nor put thy hand with the wicked to be an unrighteous Witneſs.</hi> 13. <hi>Thou shalt not follow a multitude to do evill.</hi> 14. <hi>Neither shalt thou ſpeak in a cauſe to decline after many, to wreſt judgement,</hi> the Lord doth forbid it. <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.1, 2. And <hi>Moſes</hi> in his charge to the judges, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and charged them; Firſt, to hear the cauſes between their Brethren; And, 2. To judge righteouſly between every man and his Brother. and the ſtranger that was with him: And thirdly, That they ſhould not reſpect perſons in judgement: But 4. That they ſhould hear the ſmall as wel as the great; And, 5. That they ſhould not be afraid of the face of man; for ſaith he, <hi>The judgement is Gods; and the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that it too hard for you bring it unto me, and I will hear it;</hi> as you may read <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.16, 17, 18.<note place="margin">Deut. 16.18, 19, 20.</note> And by the Law of God he is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced accurſed that perverteth the judgement of the Stranger, fatherleſs and widow; <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.19. Jehoſhaphat <hi>the King of</hi> Judah <hi>when he returned to his houſe in peace to</hi> Jeruſalem, 2 Chron: 19.1. <hi>He ſet Iudges in the Land, throughout all the fenced cities of</hi> Judah, <hi>City by City,</hi> Ver: 5. <hi>And charged them, or ſaid to the Iudges;</hi> 1. <hi>Take heed what ye do:</hi> 2. <hi>For ye judge not for man,</hi> 3. <hi>But for the Lord,</hi> 4. <hi>Who is with you in judgement. Wherefore now let the fear of the Lord be upon you, take heed, and do it:</hi> 5. <hi>For there is no Iniquity with the Lord our God,</hi> 6. <hi>Nor reſpect of perſons,</hi> 7. <hi>Nor takeing of guifts. And he charged them ſaying,, Thus shall ye do in the fear of the Lord, and with a perfect heart,</hi> See 2 <hi>Chron:</hi> 19.5, 6, 7, 8, 9. And ſuch Judges, Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and Officers we own and honour in our hearts and ſouls, who rule for God, by the holy ſpirit, and according to the holy Scriptures of the old and new Teſtament, God is our Witneſs that we ly not. And if any would have ſuch owned to rule for God, and honored with the honor given from God, who are not led by his holy Spirit, but act contrary thereunto, and contrary to the holy Scriptures; then ſpeak it out plain: For all ſuch as are owned and honored by the only true God, we honour and own.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:114692:6"/>And as concerning the office and duty of Rulers and Magiſtrates, or officers and Miniſters according to the new Teſtament; <hi>He that ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth [for God, muſt rule] with diligence,</hi> Rom: 12.8. <hi>One that ruleth well his own houſe,</hi> in the firſt place: 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 3.4. <hi>Let the Elders that rule well be counted worthy of double honour,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.17. <hi>For Rulers</hi> [that rule by the power of God] <hi>are not a terror to good works, but to the evil; wilt thou then not be afraid of the power? do that which is good, and then thou shalt have praiſe of the ſame,</hi> as you may read, <hi>Rom:</hi> 13.3. Is any power for the praiſe and encouragement of thoſe that do good, but the power of God? and is not that the higheſt power, which every ſoul is required to be ſubject to? &amp; if the ſoul be not required to be ſubject to any powers but the powers of God, which are the higher powers, then ought every Ruler amongſt men, before they rule for God, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Souls, to let their ſouls in the firſt place be ſubject to the higher powers which be of God; And then being ordained, and impower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the power of God, to rule for him, they will not be a terror to good works, (becauſe good works, they are brought forth by vertue of the power of God, and by the ſame power in him, and powers comunicated by him, to men, to rule for him, they are to be defended and encouraged by the men of God, that rule and miniſter for him, &amp; to the praiſe of his) but to the evil, <hi>Whoſe works proceeds from the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Devil,</hi> 1 Joh: 3.8, 10, 12. <hi>They are a terrour,</hi> [who are in Gods power ordained and impowered to be Miniſters of his juſtice, and peace,] <hi>wilt thou not then</hi> (as aforeſaid) <hi>be afraid of the power of God? do that which is good, and thou shalt have praiſe of the ſame: For he</hi> (that rules therein) <hi>is the miniſter of God to thee for good; but if thou do that which is evil, be afraid, for he beareth not the ſword in vain; for he is the miniſter of God;</hi> and therefore ought to diſcern between good and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, to the end that he may not diſcourage them that do well, under pretence that they do evil; nor to encourage them that do evil, under pretence that they do well: For if he err from the power of God, and want diſcerning, he may turn his ſword againſt that which it is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and preſerve, where it is not born in vain, and for want of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerning, and being gone aſtray as aforeſaid, may nouriſh vice and profanenes, &amp; ſo be a diſcourager of them that do well, and an encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rager of them that do evil, if he know not the power of God, or be er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the ſame, and have not his ſoul in ſubjection to it; That he may know them that in the power of God have their ſouls ſubjected thereunto, and are doing good by vertue of the ſame, and abſtaining alſo from evil in all its appearances. <hi>Therefore whoſoever reſiſteth the power of God</hi> (by which his miniſters of juſtice are ordained to rule for him) <hi>they reſist the ordinance of God, and shall receive to themſelves dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi> Rom: 13.1, 2, 3, 4.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And to that power and ordinance of God are we ſubject for conſcience ſake,</hi> Rom: 13.5. <hi>And the Law is good if a man uſe it lawfully, Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, that the Law is not made for</hi> [the puniſhment of] <hi>a righteous man, but for the lawleſs and diſobedient; for the ungodly and for ſinners; for unholy, and profane, for murderers, for manſlayers, for whoremongers, for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114692:6"/>
them that defile themſelves with mankind, for men-ſtealers, for lyars, for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured perſons, and ſuch like, being the fruits of the flesh:</hi> and as you may read, 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 1.8, 9, 10. &amp; <hi>Galat:</hi> 5.18, 19, 20, 21. <hi>But the fruit of the ſpirit is love, peace, long-ſuffering, gentleneſs, goodneſs, faith, meekneſs, and temperance, againſt which there is no Law:</hi> as you may read, <hi>Gal:</hi> 5.22,<note place="margin">Gal: 5.24, 25, 26.</note> 23. <hi>And they that are Chriſts, have crucified the flesh, with the affections, and luſts, and are neither deſirous of vain glory, nor of provoking, and envy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another,</hi> ver: 24, 26.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Written <date>the 3. day of the 10. month, commonly called <hi>Decemb,</hi> 1657.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Who are no <hi>Idle, Wandering, Diſſolute Perſons,</hi> nor <hi>Jeſuites;</hi> and who are no <hi>Vagabonds,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <p>SVch as are moved and directed, and commanded by the Lord God and his Spirit, to go and declare his mind and will, by the Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and according to the appointment thereof; though they goe from one Nation and Country to another, accordingly as aforeſaid, yet notwithſtanding they are neither <hi>Idle, Wandering, Diſsolute perſons</hi> nor <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> nor <hi>Vagabonds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abraham was called out of his Fathers houſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen: 12.4 Read Ge. 12. ch. &amp; Gen: 13. c.</note> 
                  <hi>and native place to go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad according to the directions of the Lord, and did ſo, and were as a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and ſojourner in a strange Land, yet he were neither an</hi> Idle, wandering diſſolute perſon, <hi>nor</hi> Jeſuite, <hi>nor</hi> Vagabond, <hi>no more are his ſeed now, though falſely they are accuſed to be ſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moſes <hi>went down into</hi> Egypt <hi>from</hi> Midian,<note place="margin">Exod: 3.1. Exo: 38.9, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>where he had been a keeper of</hi> Jethro<hi>'s sheep, to do the will of the Lord, &amp; yet he were neither an</hi> idle wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering perſon, <hi>nor a</hi> Jeſuite <hi>or</hi> Vagabond, <hi>though</hi> Pharaoh <hi>the king then of</hi> Egypt <hi>falſly accuſed the ſervants of the Lord to be idle fellows, or to take the people off from their work. And</hi> Pharaoh <hi>the king regarded not the words of the Lords meſſengers, but accounted them vain; and as the falſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing ſpirit did then, ſo doth it now, though the perſons guided thereby profeſs more then</hi> Pharaoh <hi>did, and accuſeth them to be</hi> idle, wandring, diſſolute perſons, <hi>or</hi> Jeſuites <hi>and</hi> Vagabonds <hi>that are not, no more then</hi> Moſes <hi>the ſervant of the Lord was then.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Elijah <hi>the ſervant of the Lord was not an</hi> idle wandring diſſolute perſon, <hi>nor a</hi> Jeſuit, <hi>nor</hi> Vagabond,<note place="margin">Exod: 5: 4.5, 6, 7, 8, 9, verſ. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>though he paſſed much up and down the country in obedience to the Lord, and went to beg, or ask ſom relief of the widow of</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repta; <hi>And if any of the Lords meſſengers should do ſo now, would not this generation of men accuſe them for running wandring abroad a begging, &amp; ſo accuſe them to be idle wandring diſſolute perſons, and vagabonds, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers of the Nation. Did not king</hi> Ahab <hi>then king of</hi> Iſrael <hi>accuſe the ſaid</hi> Elijah <hi>the ſervant of the Lord falſly; and ſay, he was his enemy, &amp; a troubler of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>but it was not ſo,</hi> viz. <hi>That he was a troubler of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>but of the wicked: Therefore the ſervant of the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 King 19. ch. 1 King: 17.10, 11.</note> 
                  <hi>(to caſt off the falſe accuſation charged upon him by the king, and to clear his own innocency) ſaid to the king that it was he,</hi> viz. <hi>the king and his Fathers houſe that was ſo, even the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers of</hi> Iſrael <hi>the people of the Lord; And ſo the falſe accuſing ſpirit in this generation is apt to charge the Servants of the Lord falſly, &amp; to ſeek to lay upon them that which the accuſers themſelves are guilty of, as</hi> Ahab <hi>and his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114692:7"/>
fathers houſe was, when the innocency of the innocent, though falſly accuſed, is clear, and ſtands juſtified in the ſight and account of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Diſciples of Christ ſent forth by his own power, when he were perſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally amongſt them, was commanded to go abroad in the Countreys, to the lost sheep of the houſe of Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 10.5, 6. Mat. 10.9, 10.</note> 
                  <hi>and forbidden taking thought what to eat, drink or put on, and commanded to take neither ſilver nor gold nor braſs in their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, yet they was no idle wandring diſsolute perſons, nor Ieſuites, nor Vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonds; But if any be ſent of the Lord now, and forbidden to take any ſilver or gold in their purſes; This generation would be ready to accuſe them to be idle wandering diſſolute perſons, mad men &amp; Vagabonds; might not the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples that Chriſt ſo ſent have objected and ſaid, Lord, how shall we do to be provided for, when we come amongſt Strangers and in other Countries, if we must not take any Silver nor Gold, nor Braſſe in our Purſes? had we not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter take Silver and Gold &amp; Braſſe in our Purſes, that we may make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion thereby for ourſelves, when we come amongst Strangers (&amp; ſo ſtop their mouthes) rather then to rely upon them? &amp; will not they be ready to ſay, Theſe are idle looſe fellowes, mad men and Vagabonds, that wanders a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to live upon other mens labours, and cannot otherwiſe tell how to get a living? They neither have Silver nor Gold nor Braſſe in their Purſes; do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that have meanes to live on go out thus, when they are to go into farr Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and amongſt Strangers, except they be idle wandering diſſolute perſons, and Vagabonds, ſuch as have no Silver nor Gold to take in their Purſes? yet notwithſtanding the Diſciples of Chriſt that were ſo ſent as aforeſaid, were neiher idle wandering diſſolute perſons, nor</hi> Jeſuits <hi>nor</hi> Vagabonds; <hi>No more are the Servants of Chrſt, though they may ſo go, now, in obedience to the command and councell of Chriſt, yet this generation of men are ready to accuſe them, to be idle wandering diſſolute perſons, or</hi> Jeſuits <hi>or</hi> Vagabonds, <hi>as that generation of men accuſed the ſaid ſervants of Chriſt aforementioned, and others that ſucceeded them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 4.13. Acts. 24.5 6.</note> 
                  <hi>to be ignorant unlearned men, and deceivers, and turbulent pestilent fellowes, mad men, and ringleaders of Sects and the like, though they was not, but that the falſe accuſeing ſpirit of the world was then, and of ancient ſtanding is now, yet accuſtomed with that work.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Before Chriſt aſcended he called his ſervants together, &amp; gave them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to waite at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>till they was indued with power from on high, Saying, then shall ye be my witneſſes, not only in</hi> Judea &amp; Jeruſalem, <hi>but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to the uttermoſt parts of the earth:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 1.4 &amp; 8. verſ.</note> Might they not then have objected, and ſaid Lord, would it not be better (if thy excellency would be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) to chuſe out Meſſengers for thy own work in every Countrey that are native and Inhabitants, then to ſend us as ſtrangers amongſt them, where we are generally to them unknown? ſhall we not by that be hardlyer thought of, becauſe we are not (to any of them) known? and will not that be a meanes to bring us into great ſufferings &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions amongſt them,<note place="margin">Mat. 4.18.19, 20.21.12. Mat. 9.9. Tit. 1 16.</note> and when we come abroad in far Countries &amp; beyond Seas, where we are not at all amongſt them known, will it not give them cauſe to ſay we are Jeſuits, or idle wandering diſſolute per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and vagabonds? yet not withſtanding what they might have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected againſt ſuch a ſending, (as leaving eſtates, relations behind them,) and coming under falſe cenſures and great perſecution, they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:114692:7"/>
gave up freeely and went, leaving behind them their eſtates and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations: But ſuch as are moved of the Lord to do ſo now, (in the croſſe to their wills, and through the tryall of their faith and exerciſe of their patience) they are hardly judged of by thoſe that are at eaſe in the fleſh, and do greatly ſuffer by reaſon of the ſubtilty of the ſerpent that is clothed over and hid under a pretence and profeſſion of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, profeſſing God in words, but unto every good work are abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and reprobate; as ſuch like aforetime was.</p>
               <p>When the Church was met at <hi>Antioh,</hi> as they <hi>miniſtred and faſted,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 13.1, 2.</note> the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> ſaid, <hi>Seperate me Barnabas and Saul for the work where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto I have appointed them, and they being ſent forth by the holy Ghoſt, they departed unto</hi> Selucia, <hi>and from thence they paſsing over Seas ſayled to</hi> Cyprus, Act: 13.4. <hi>and ſo to</hi> Salamis, <hi>ver.</hi> 5. And yet notwithſtanding they were neither idle wandring diſſolute perſons, nor Jeſuits,<note place="margin">Act. 18.18 19, 20, 21, 22, 23.</note> nor va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabonds, no more are ſuch that are ſent by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> now, though they may paſs abroad in ſeveral Countreys and over Seas, about the work of the Lord now to act by his ſpirit as they are directed, as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> afore mentioned did then.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Likewiſe</hi> Paul <hi>and</hi> Barnabas, <hi>they paſſed much abroad in the countreys after that, for after they had been at</hi> Salamis, <hi>they paſſed through the iſle un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> Paphos; Acts 13.6. <hi>And did the work of the Lord for which they was ſent by the holy Ghoſts order and appointment: And when</hi> Paul <hi>and his company looſed from</hi> Paphos, Act. 13.13. <hi>They paſsing through the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries came to</hi> Perga <hi>in</hi> Pamphilia, <hi>and when they departed from</hi> Perga <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, paſsing over the countries they came to</hi> Antioch <hi>in</hi> Piſidea, <hi>and did the work of the Lord, appointed them by the holy Ghoſt there alſo,</hi> Acts 13. from ver. 14. to ver. 45. <hi>But then (as now) the Iews, the old envious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, being offended at the truth, they out of their envy, ſpoke againſt thoſe things which was ſpoken by</hi> Paul, <hi>and ſo was in an errour therein, and alſo for contradicting and blaſpheming him and the truth;</hi> ver. 45. <hi>Yet they that was ſo contradicted, and as aforeſaid, was neither</hi> Jeſuits, <hi>nor</hi> idle wandring diſſolute perſons, <hi>nor</hi> Vagabonds, <hi>but they was the dear ſervants of the Lord, and waxed bold againſt the deceit, to declare and teſtifie the truth of the Lord,</hi> Act. 13. from ver. 45. to ver. 50. <hi>But though they was neither Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, nor idle wandring diſolute perſons, nor vagabonds, no more then ſuch as are the Lords Meſſengers now; yet the envious profeſſours the</hi> Jews <hi>ſtirred up the devout and honorable women ſo called, and the chief men of the City, and raiſed perſecution againſt</hi> Paul <hi>and</hi> Barnabas, <hi>and banished them, or at leaſt expelled them out of their Coaſts, but they shook off the duſt off their feet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and came to</hi> Iconium, ſee Acts 13.50. <hi>And the ſervants of the Lord that were ſo perſecuted and banished were at peace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 13.50, 51.</note> 
                  <hi>and justified in the ſight of the Lord, and the Diſciples were filled with joy, and with the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The profeſſors of them times, and the chief men of the Citie, and even ſuch as were accounted devout and honorable amongſt them, they were in great error in being ſo readie to be ſtirred up by the envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous profeſſors, and ſo raiſe perſecution againſt the ſervants of the Lord, and baniſh or expel them out of their Coaſts, inſomuch that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114692:8"/>
they ſhook off the duſt of their feet to be a witneſſe againſt them, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the command and counſel of the Lord Jeſus; and then the chief men of the City, and the profeſſors, (and as aforeſaid) they did not believe that the Apoſtles and ſervants of the Lord was the Lords Miniſters and Meſſengers that ſo paſſed abroad in the countries and over Seas, into many Nations, no more then the chief men in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Cities; and ſuch as are old, envious profeſſors, and alſo them that are accounted devout and honourable by men, do believe that the Servants of the Lord are the Lords Miniſters and Meſſengers now, that paſſe abroad in the Countries and over ſeas into other Nations; but being envious againſt the truth, they raiſe perſecution againſt the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Lord, and are readie to expel (or baniſh) them out of their coaſts, and call them idle, wandering, diſſolute perſons, or Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, or Vagabonds: ſo void of diſcerning of truth from error are they, being prejudiced in their minds againſt the Lords Meſſengers, (as ſuch in the curſed nature aforetime were, and now are) that they cannot abide that truth ſhould be trulie declared, or entertained in the families, and cities, and countries where they are; but as the witneſſe of God ariſeth, and anſwers to the judgments of God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and that which ſhall be againſt them for their diſobedience to the truth, and envie againſt the truth, and ſervants and meſſengers thereof, they ſhall then be aſhamed of ſuch their ignorant or wilful a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and crie out in the bitterneſſe of their ſpirit againſt themſelves for ſo acting, as aforeſaid, when the Book of conſcience is opened, and the judgement of Chriſt againſt them is pronounced.</p>
               <p>Therefore while you have time, prize it, and fear the Lord God, ſo will you not oppoſe nor perſecute his ſervants and meſſengers, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them, and delight in the truth, as to you it is revealed.</p>
               <p>And after that <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> had been baniſhed, as aforeſaid, or expelled out of their Coaſts at <hi>Antioch</hi> in <hi>Piſidea,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 13.</note> and thoſe Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, when they had been in the ſynagogue there, and ſate ſilent till the legal Preacher or Reader had done, who after that declared the truth in oppoſition to the deceit; but the enmitie ſtanding in the minds of the old envious profeſſors and citizens, as aforeſaid, they did not onelie act Antichriſts part in rejecting the truth declared, to caſt it out of the peoples affections, by contradicting and blaſpheming the Lords Meſſengers, but they proceeded further in Antichriſts work, as to reject and baniſh, or expel the ſaid Meſſengers of Chriſt out of their coaſts; and ſuch an Antipathie there is between Chriſt and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, that the Antichriſtians now, though formal and feigned profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Chriſtians, they cannot indure that the truth, and true real Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and ſervants of Chriſt ſhould be entertained and abide in their Coaſts, but endeavours are uſed to get a Law to whip them (by the advice or conſent of the profeſſed Miniſters of Chriſt) till blood come, and then banniſh or expel them out of their coaſts, who are the Lords true Meſſengers and Miniſters, according to the order and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of the Holie Ghoſt, and ſo ſend them awaie with a Paſſe, to the end that (as much as in the will of corrupt man is) truth may
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114692:8"/>
be kept under, from growing and taking place in the peoples hearts and affections; but though Antichriſt hath now, as then he had, ſuch as will ſo act his part under ſpecious pretences againſt the truth, yet the proſperitie of the truth is a torment to the adverſaries thereof.</p>
               <p>And when <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> had been banniſhed as aforeſaid, yet they were not diſcouraged, but waxed bold in the Lord, and afterward went to <hi>Iconium,</hi> and went both together into the ſynagogue of the Jews, though they had not the command there to ſtand up, as the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh-prieſts do in the high-places; and the ſaid <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> ſo ſpake, that a great multitude both of the Jews, and alſo of the Greeks, believed: But then [as now] the unbelievers that were Jewes, even great profeſſors, they ſtirred up the Gentiles, and made their minds e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil affected againſt the Brethren, <hi>Act.</hi> 14.1, 2. Yet notwithſtanding they abode a long time, ſpeaking boldlie in the Lord; but the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the Citie were divided (then, as now, where the truth taketh place in the hearts and affections of ſome of the Citizens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) and part held with the Jews, and part with the Apoſtles, <hi>Act.</hi> 14.3, 4. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that there was then (as oft-times now is, or of late hath bin) an aſſault made both of the profeſſors and people, together with their Rulers, to uſe them that received the truth, and the Lords Meſſengers both, deſpitefullie, and ſtone them, <hi>Act.</hi> 4. Yet they that were thus aſſaulted by the people, profeſſors, and Rulers, and againſt them had ſuch crueltie intended, they were neither idle, wandering, diſſolute perſons, nor Jeſuits, nor Vagabonds, no more are ſuch as the envious profeſſors falſelie accuſeth to the Magiſtrates to be ſo now.</p>
               <p>And after that crueltie intended againſt the ſaid ſervants of the Lord, and as before-mentioned, after they left <hi>Iconium,</hi> as it were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, they went abroad in the Countries without a Paſſe-port from the ſaid Rulers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to <hi>Listea</hi> and <hi>Derbe,</hi> Cities of <hi>Lyconia,</hi> and unto the Region that lieth round about, and there they preached the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, <hi>Act.</hi> 14.6, 7. but though they ſo paſſed abroad in the Countries or Cities, and Regions round about without any mans Paſſe-port, or as aforeſaid, yet they were neither Jeſuits, nor idle, wandering, diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute perſons, or vagrants, no more then ſuch the Lords Meſſengers that paſſe abroad in the Countries to declare the minde of the Lord, are now, though this generation falſlie accuſe them to be ſo, and are readie to get a Law made intentionallie againſt them, to puniſh them under ſuch falſe cenſures and denominations; but yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the innocencie of the innocent ſtands clear in the ſight of the Lord; and his ſervants and meſſengers that are ſo accuſed as aforeſaid, doth and will ſtand juſtified in the ſight and account of the Lord, when the wicked, whoever they are, that are troublers of them, ſhal be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and juſtlie condemned before the Lord, when he taketh venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance on them that are the troublers of his children and ſervants, and as you may read, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9. v</p>
               <p>And whil'ſt the aforenamed ſervants and meſſengers of Chriſt that paſſed abroad in the Countries, and as aforeſaid,<note place="margin">Act. 14.6.</note> was preaching the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114692:9"/>
Goſpel in thoſe places and Regions laſt mentioned,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 14.19, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> as <hi>Liſtra, Derbe</hi> and the Regions round about, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> there came thither certain profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, as Jews from <hi>Antioch</hi> and <hi>Iconiom,</hi> places and cities where the ſaid ſervants of the Lord had declared the truth, and from one of them places were baniſhed, as is apprehended, and at the other, towards them much evil by Rulers and people was intended, as aforeſaid, who perſwaded the people againſt them; and having ſtoned <hi>Paul,</hi> drew him out of the Citie, ſuppoſing he had been dead: Mark this, you that are envious profeſſors, and all ſuch as are perſecutors, and read your examples by comparing the fruits of your envious ſpirits, with the fruits of ſuch as ſo acted before you againſt the Lords truth and his meſſengers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Howbeit <hi>Paul</hi> was not dead when they ſuppoſed that he he had ſo been, upon the aforeſaid perſecution and ſtoning, but he roſe up, and came into the Citie, and the next daie he departed with <hi>Barnabas</hi> to <hi>Derbe,</hi> and when they had preached the Goſpel to that Citie, and had taught many, they returned again to <hi>Liſtra,</hi> and through the countries to <hi>Iconium,</hi> where ſo much evil were, and had been intended againſt them, as aforeſaid; and from thence to <hi>Antioch,</hi> and at <hi>Antioch</hi> in <hi>Piſsidia,</hi> they had been baniſhed or expelled out of their coaſts, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forementioned, confirming the ſouls of the Diſciples, exhorting them alſo to continue in the faith, and that we muſt through great tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on enter into the Kingdom of God. And after that, and when they had paſſed throughout the Countrie of <hi>Piſidia,</hi> they came to <hi>Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philia,</hi> and when they had paſſed abroad in the Countrie, and had preached the word in <hi>Perga,</hi> they went abroad in the Countries down into <hi>Attalia,</hi> and from thence paſſing over Sea, ſailed to <hi>Antioch,</hi> from whence they had been recommended by the Grace of God for the work which they fulfilled, <hi>Act.</hi> 14.19. to the end. <hi>Act.</hi> 13.1, 2. And though they paſſed ſo much abroad in the Countries, and beyond ſeas to declare the truth, and met with ſuch great perſecution, and had ſo much evil intended againſt them by Rulers and people, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they had not any Paſſe-port or certificate for their travelling under the hand or ſeal of any Port-Graves, Bailiffs, Conſtables of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, Conſervators of the Peace of Cities, Corporations, Towns, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or Countries and Provinces, Sheriffs, Mayors, Keepers of Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Liberties, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> nor from under the hand or ſeal of any called Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of the peace, or any other head Officer or Officers of ſuch afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid repective places, that ever we read of, yet they were no Vagrants, nor idle, diſſolute, wandering perſons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> No more are the ſervants of the Lord now, though they do, and may paſſe much abroad in the Countries, and over ſeas, to do the will of the Lord, as he them moves thereunto, and without any mans Paſſe-port, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as the aforeſaid ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Lord did, though they may paſſe through many tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the footſteps of the flock of Chriſt, and pathes to the entrance into the Kingdom of God.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. F.</signed>
               </closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:114692:9"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
